Guide to the Charlton Thomas Lewis Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charlton Thomas Lewis papers
1612-1904
MS 981
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes, 1 folio)
The major part of the papers consist of a collection of autographs of literary, intellectual, and political figures, largely English and American, compiled by Charlton T. Lewis.Included are such notables as Robert Browning, Washington Irving, William James, John Stuart Mill, Louis Orléans, comte de Paris, Richelieu, Talleyrand, Alfred Lord Tennyson, Voltaire, John Wesley, and Walt Whitman. There is also personal correspondence addressed to Lewis and his wife, Margaret P. Sherrand Lewis, as well as essays, addresses, and an unpublished novel by Lewis, and a speech on Italian immigrants by Margaret P. Lewis.
Lewis, Charlton T. (Charlton Thomas), 1834-1904
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James McKeen Lewis and Mrs. Lincoln MacVeagh in 1947.
Scope and Contents
The Charlton Thomas Lewis Papers fall into two sections. The first consists of a collection of autographs of famous literary, intellectual, and political figures compiled by Lewis, and of letters addressed to him and his wife, Margaret P. (Sherrand) Lewis by notables of their acquaintence. Beginning with two documents signed by members of the British Privy Council in 1612 and 1615, the collection contains letters and other items from such prominent figures as Robert Browning, Washington Irving, William James, the first duke of Marlborough, John Stuart Mill, Louis Orléans (comte de Paris; an essay,"L'Esprit de conquête en 1870"), the due de Richelieu, Talleyrand, Alfred Lord Tennyson, Voltaire, John Wesley, and Walt Whitman. Also included are several menu cards signed by numerous individuals. These letters and documents have been arranged chronologically, however, an alphabetical list is provided in the register. Note that the folder numbers are listed non-sequentially as a result.
The remainder of the papers consists of writings by Lewis, as well as one by Margaret C. (Lewis) MacVeagh; included are an unpublished novel, sermons, addresses, and essays on historical and legal topics. There are in addition several oversize items, to wit, Lewis' Harvard L.L.D. diploma, two certificates, and a plan of Ticonderoga.
These papers were donated to Yale University in 1947 by James McKeen Lewis and Mrs. Lincoln MacVeagh.
Biographical / Historical
CHARLTON THOMAS Lewis, son of Joseph J. and Mary Sinton (Miner) Lewis, was born on February 25,1834, in West Chester, Pa. He was Class Poet, and was especially distinguished in mathematics during his college course.
After graduation he studied law in his father's office in West Chester until the spring of 1854, when he entered the ministry of the Methodist Episcopal Church, and was appointed by the Philadelphia Conference to the Newark Circuit. He was stationed first in Wilmington, Del., in March, 1855, and the following year at the Broad Street Church, Philadelphia. He then accepted an appointment as Professor of Languages in the State Normal University of Illinois, at Bloomington. After a year there, he as Professor of Mathematics a year, and then Professor of Greek in Troy (N. Y.) University. He was Acting President of the latter institution in 1862. In December of that year he became pastor of an Independent Methodist Church in Cincinnati.
In 1863-1864 he was Deputy Commissioner of Internal Revenue at Washington, and then removed to New York City, where he remained afterward engaged in the practice of law. He began his New York career in association with Hon. Samuel S. Cox, in the firm of Lewis & Cox, which devoted itself largely to suits arising in the construction of Internal Revenue Laws. After the reduction of Internal Revenue to a peace basis, he gained a high reputation as an authority on insurance law, and for more than twenty years was counsel to the Mutual Life Insurance Company of New York. In 1898 he lectured at Cornell University on the Principles of Insurance, and in 1899 at Harvard and Columbia Universities on Life Insurance. From 1873 to 1878 he was Secretary and Treasurer of the Chamber of Life Insurance of the United States. He was also a Director in the International Bell Telephone Company, North American Trust Company, United States Mortgage and Trust Company, and other business corporations.
For many years he made a study of the question of treatment of criminals, and did most effective service in behalf of reform in the administration of prisons and public charities. From 1881 he was Chairman of the Executive Committee of the New York Prison Association, and from 1893 President of the Association, annually reelected. He was Delegate of the United States to the International Prison Congress at Paris in 1895, in the same year Chairman of the Commission to Revise the Penal Laws of New Jersey, Vice-President of the National Prison Association in 1897, and Delegate of New Jersey to the National Prison Congress at Philadelphia in 1901. He was a member of the Board of Managers of the New Jersey State Reformatory in 1901, and was reappointed in 1903. During the last ten years he was also President of the State Charities Aid Association of New Jersey.
He was a brilliant classical scholar and spent many years in the preparation of "Harper's Latin Dictionary," 1879; new edition 1896. With this as a basis he also published "The Latin Dictionary for Schools," 1889, and "The Elementary Latin Dictionary," 1891. He translated Bengel's "Gnomon of the New Testament," 2 vols., 1861-1863, which has been often republished as the Tract Society's "Critical English New Testament," and wrote "A History of Germany," founded on David Müller's "History of the German People," 1874. In 1895 he edited "Harper's Book of Facts," and in 1901 a translation of "The Letters of Prince Bismarck to his Wife." Besides these he wrote literary, essays, poems, anniversary addresses, and contributions to journals and newspapers. In 1870-1871 he was Managing Editor of the New York Evening Post. He was one of the most steadfast members of the Greek Club of New York, which has met at stated intervals every winter for forty years to read Greek together, and during this time has been in course more than once through the entire range of Greek literature. He was also a member of the New York Historical Society, the American Mathematical Society, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and many social and literary clubs. He gave little time to politics, but was a Delegate from New Jersey to the National Democratic Convention in 1896. He received the degree of Doctor of Philosophy from New York University in 1877, and Doctor of Laws from Harvard University in 1903.
Dr. Lewis cared little about personal fame but sought every kind of knowledge for its own sake, and after mastering it delighted in changing his field of study. The night and morning before his sudden illness he passed at Columbia University Library pursuing studies in Dante, in which he bad been greatly interested in his last years.
For many years Dr. Lewis resided at Morristown, N. J., and there he died, of cerebro-spinal meningitis, on May 26 1904. He was 70 years of age.
He married, on July 25, 1861, Nancy Dunlap, daughter of Joseph and Elizabeth (Farley) McKeen, of Brunswick, Me., who died in 1883. He afterward married Margaret P., daughter of Rev. Thomas Sherrard and his wife, Valeria G. Sherrard, of Tecumseh, Michigan. Of the four children by the first marriage three are living. The elder son (Yale 1833) died in. 1887. The younger son (Yale 1886) is Emily Sanford Professor of English Literature in Yale University. One of the daughters graduated from Smith College in 1895. By the second marriage he had a son and a daughter, who, with their mother, survived.
From Yale University Obituary Record.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Italians -- United States; Law; Autographs; Sermons; Clergy; Lawyers; Lewis, Charlton T. (Charlton Thomas), 1834-1904; Lewis, Margaret P. Sherrand
- Inventory, 1612-1904, undated; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence and autograph collection, 1612-1904, undated
    - Abbot, George, abp. of Canterbury, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abbott, John Stevens Cabot, 1869 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Arnold, Sir Edwin, 1888 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bacon, Theodore, 1854 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bancroft, George, 1877 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1865 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bigelow, John, 1896 February 4, 1897 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bigelow, Poultney, 1895 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bolton, William Orde-Powlett, 2nd baron, 1822 November (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Browning, Robert, 1864 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Buchanan, James, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Butler, Benjamin F., 1865 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Caesar, Sir Julius, 1612 September 1, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carnavon, Howard Molyneux Herbert, 4th earl, 1883 November 19, 1884 January 4, 1885 July 21, August 31, 1886 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 17, 18)
    - Chamberlain, Joshua Lawrence, 1865 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cleveland, Stephen Grover, 1904 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Coke, Sir Edward, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Collier, Robert Laird, 1868 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Conway, Moncure David, 1889 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cozzens, Frederick Swartout, 1864 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Crittenden, John Jordan, 1862 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Curtis, George William, 1869 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - D'Arusmont, Frances (Wright), 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Drisler, Henry, 1891 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Eliot, Charles William, 1897 September 30, 1899 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Ellesmere, Thomas Edgerton, baron, 1612 September 1, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Fechtler, Charles Albert, [ca. 1870 Apr] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Fentoun, Thomas Erskine, viscount, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ferris, Morris Patterson, 1900 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Field, Henry Martyn, 1886 oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Garfield, James Abram, 1872 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Gildersleeve, Basil Lanneau, 1881 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1872 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Godwin, Parke, 1870 March 14, 1900 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 14, 21)
    - Goodwin, Maud (Wilder), 1897 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Greville, Fulke, Baron Brooke, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1904 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Hancock, Winfield Scott, 1864 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, 3rd earl, 1824 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Harper, Joseph Wesley, Jr., 1887 January 14, 1895 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 19, 20)
    - Hawthorne, Julian, 1885 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Houghton, Richard Monckton Mill, 1st baron, 1864 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Irving, Washington, 1857 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Jackson, John P[eter?], [ca. 1870 Dec] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - James, Thomas L., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - James, William, 1903 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Kotzebue, August Friedrich Ferdinand von, 1790 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Knollys of Greys, William Knollys, baron, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lane, Gardiner Martin, 1897 September 28, December 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Lane, George Martin, 1888 April 5, October 4, 1889 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lanman, Charles Rockwell, 1884 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lennox, Ludovick Stuart, 2nd Duke of Lennox and Duke of Richmond, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Leonard, J A, 1904 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lewis, Charlton Thomas, 1862 June 16, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Lieber, Francis, 1869 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lind-Goldschmidt, Jenny Maria, 1851 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Lowell, James Russell, 1883 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lyell, Sir Charles, 1845 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lyndhurst, John Singleton Copley, baron, 1828 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - McClellan, George Blinton, 1864 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - McDonald, Flora (Macdonald), 1751 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - MacVeagh, Wayne, 1881 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Maltby, Edward, bp, of Durham, 1838 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Marlborough, John Churchill, 1st duke, 1718 December 10, 1727 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mathew, Theobold, 1845 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Mill, John Stuart, 1866 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Moore, Thomas, 1836 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Morgan, Morris Hicky, 1897 September 29, October 8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Mornington, William Wellesley Pole, 3rd earl, 1807 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Morrill, Justin Smith, 1864 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Northampton, Henry Howard, earl, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Nottingham, Charles Howard, earl, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Orléans, Louis Philip Albert, comte de Paris, 1870 December 6, 1870 December (Box 1, Folder 14, 15)
    - Parker, Sir Hyde, 1756 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Parker, Joel, 1865 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Parry, Sir Thomas, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Peel, Sir Robert, 1822 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pembroke, William Herbert, 3rd earl, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pierce, Franklin, 1858 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Plunkett, William Conyngham Plunkett, 1st baron, 1807 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Portal, Antoine, baron de, 1819 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Porter, Noah, 1872 June 20, 1883 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 16, 17)
    - Portland, William Cavendish Bentinck-Scott, 5th duke, 1837 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pratt, Sir Charles, 1754 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Price, Thomas Randolph, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Richelieu, Armand Emmanuel Sophie Septemanie du Plessis, duc de, 1816 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Riis, Jacob August, 1903 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Rives, William Cabell, 1829 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Rochester, Robert Carr, viscount See also:Somerset, Robert Carr, earl, 1612 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Romero, Matías, 1865 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Rop, John, 1834 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ross, Sir John, 1819 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Schaff, Philip, 1885 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Schumacher, Ludwig, 1889 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Sessions, D R, 1885 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Seward, William H., 1865 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Shrewsbury, Gilbert Talbot, earl, 1612 September 1, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Smalley, George Washburn, 1880 October 13, 14 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Somerset, Robert Carr, earl See also: Rochester, Robert Carr, viscount, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1886 March 23, 1888 January 21, 1896 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 19, 20)
    - Stockton, Frank Richard, 1895 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Storrs, Richard Salter, [1870] June 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Suffolk, Thomas Howard, earl, 1612 September 1, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sumner, Charles, 1871 February 3, [ca. 1872] (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent, 1819 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, 1st baron, 1842 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Thacher, Thomas Anthony, 1862 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Voltaire, Françoise Marie Arouet, 1765 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Wagner, M, Lewis, [1865] June 13 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Wallenstein, earl de, 1826 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Watterson, Henry, 1904 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Webster, Daniel, 1838 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Weiss, [underline], bp. of Strasbourg, 1842 November (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Wendt, S, 1832 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Wesley, John, 1790 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Wetterstedt, graf, 1829 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - White, Andrew Dickson, 1869 June 9, 15, 1896 October 8 1901 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 13, 20, 21)
    - White, Charles, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - White, Horace, 1900 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Whitman, Walt, 1887 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Williams, Thomas, 1833 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Wilson, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Wilson, Joshua, 1830 March 20, 1846 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 7, 10)
    - Winkler, Karl Gottfried Theodor, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Winwood, Sir Ralph, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Witzleben, Karl August Friedrich von, 1829 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Wood, Fernando, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Worcester, Edward Somerset, 4th earl, 1612 September 1, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Wotton of Marley, Edward Wotton, baron, 1612 September 1, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Yarborough, Charles Anderson-Pelham, 1st baron, 1816 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Yates, James, 1770 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Yenn, John, 1815 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Yonge, Sir George, 1786 April 21, 1791 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Young, Arthur, [1780-1790] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Young, John, 1778 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Youngman, William, 1821 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Zouche, Edward Curzon, baron, 1612 September 1, 1615 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Writings
    - Sermons, 1855-1860, undated (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
    - "Lafayette and the Historians", 1895 November 19 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "The Character of Lafayette", 1896 February 22 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Address at the Alumni Meeting", 1903 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "The Condition of Moslem Women under Islam", undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "Copyright", undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "The Interest of Society in the Reform of Penal Law", undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "The Professional Spirit and Scientific Medicine", undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "The Tax on Life Insurance Policies", undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Unpublished novel, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Two commencement addresses, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous addresses, notes, etc. re: Penal codes and reform, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Address on the Revolutionary War, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Two notebooks of addresses and notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "Address" and notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Margaret Charlton (Lewis) MacVeagh: address concerning Italian immigrants, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Certificates
    - New York State Supreme Court: certificate as attorney and counsellor at law, 1863 November 30 (Box 3)
    - New Jersey: appointment as commissioner of the reformatory, 1903 May 1 (Box 3)
    - Harvard University: Doctor of Laws diploma, 1903 June 24 (Box 3)
  - "A Plan of the Town and Fort of Carillon at Ticonderoga; with the Attack made by the British Army Commanded by Genl. Abercrombie, 8 July 1758. Engraved by Thos. Jefferys…", undated (Box 3)